Guide to the Edward LaChapelle avalanche control video collection 1950-1970
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Edward LaChapelle avalanche control video collection
1950-1970
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0439
LaChapelle, Edward R.
19 16mm films, 10 VHS videocassettes, 2 Betacam videocassettes
The Edward LaChapelle avalanche control video collection (1950-1970) consists of films about avalanche danger, control and research at Utah ski areas and around the world. The collection also includes some of LaChapelle's home movies and other ski related footage. Edward LaChapelle was an American glaciologist, mountaineer, skier, author, and professor and a pioneer in Avalanche research, safety and forecasting.
Biographical Note
Edward Randle "Ed" LaChapelle (1926-2007) was born in May 31 Tacoma, Washington. After studying physics and math at the University of Puget Sound and spending time at the Swiss Federal Institute for Snow and Avalanche Research he joined the United States Forest Service as a snow ranger in Alta, Utah in 1952.
In addition to his two decades of work at Alta's avalanche center, LaChapelle was professor of atmospheric sciences and geophysics at the University of Washington from 1967 to 1982 and professor emeritus until his death. He also researched the subject at the Institute for Arctic and Alpine Research (INSTAAR) of the University of Colorado at Boulder from 1973-1977 and was involved in the 1968 development of the avalanche transceiver beacon. Edward LaChapelle died of a heart attack at Colorado's Monarch Ski Area on February 1, 2007.
The Edward LaChapelle avalanche control video collection (1950-1970) consists of films about avalanche danger, control and research. Several films document early avalanche control done at Alta, Utah. The collection also includes some of LaChapelle's home movies and other ski related footage.
The materials are arranged by format type.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also Edward LaChapelle's 35mm slides, located with the photograph collections, and his ex-wife Dolores LaChapelle's photograph collection (P0981).
Alta (Utah); Avalanches; Avalanches--Control; Avalanches--Control--Utah; Science; Sports and Recreation; Moving Images; Moving images
- Unidentified 16mm film, undated; 16mm film (Reel 1)
- Wasatch National Forest, 1965; 16mm film (Reel 2)
- Wasatch National Forest, 1965; 16mm film (Reel 3)
- Metamorphism and compression of wet snow, undated; 16mm film (Reel 4)
  Filmed by Gorow Wakehame and Katutosi Tusima, instructors in low temperature science, Hokkaido University, Suppero, Japan.
- Footage of avalanche damage at Wallace, Idaho, undated; 16mm film (Reel 5)
  Filmed by Monty Atwater for Disney. Footage of Honeycomb Ridge and cornice blast.
- Avalanche control out-takes, 1963; 16mm film (Reel 6)
  1963 Material not used in film "Avalanche Control." Includes scenes of control work and various avalanche artillery such as the original muzzle-loading avalauncher.
- Alta, 1957; 16mm film (Reel 7)
  Various scenes of terrain skiers, avalanche control and snow tests. Material of historical interest.
- San Juan Mountain avalanche scenes, 1970s; 16mm film (Reel 8)
- Avalanche Control raw footage, 1963; 16mm film (Reel 9)
  Original footage used in Avalanche Control. Scenes of test skiing, fracture line profile, slope measurements, assorted weapons firing: recoilless rifle, 75mm howitzer, avalauncher (original model).
- Snow plowing and avalanche control scenes at Alta, 1960s; 16mm film (Reel 10)
- Avalanche control uses publicity reel, undated; 16mm film (Reel 11)
- Avalanche control outtakes, 1960s; 16mm film (Reel 12)
  Various scenes of firing artillery, shell bursts and avalanche releases prepared to illustrate avalanche control on a television program.
- Avalanche dynamics, undated; 16mm film (Reel 13)
- Andre Roche avalanche footage, 1960s; 16mm film (Reel 14-15)
  Scenes of avalanche control with various weapons, avalanche releases, observation techniques and details involved in the taking a fracture line profile. Some of this footage was used in "Avalanche Control."
- Alta, circa 1957; 16mm film (Reel 16)
  Various scenes of terrain, snowplowing, avalanche control. General historical interest.
- Japan snow technology, 1972; 16mm film (Reel 17-18)
  Directed by Ed LaChapelle.
- Alta scenes, 1950s; 16mm film (Reel 19)
  Home movies, footage of people firing guns, cornice kicking and some ski cuts.
- Avalanche awareness: a question of balance, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 20)
- Avalanche control, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 21)
  A KSL news broadcast about an avalanche which took place in Little Cottonwood Canyon.
- Avalanche hazards part 2, 1966; VHS videocassette Black and white (Cassette 22)
  Produced by The United States Army. 27 minutes.
- VHS duplicates, VHS videocassette (Cassette 23-29)
  Dubs of items 2-22.
- Betacam duplicates, Betacam videocassette (Cassette 30-31)
  Dubs of items 2-16, 19.